Finding Aid for the Edouard Roditi Papers LSC.0644
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Manuscripts by Édouard Roditi and others.
  - Jewish writers and artists in Rumania by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 36)
    Jews in Rumania--political and social conditions
    Artists, Jews
    Authors, Jews
  - Jews of Djerba by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Jews in Djerba
    Jewish way of life
  - Jews of Djerba by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
  - Jews of Djerba by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Published in MENORAH JOURNAL, New York, Spring/Summer 1955.
  - Jews of Djerba - corrections and research material by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 36)
  - Job of living by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Included with this is Roditi's holograph note, "Early draft of an unfinished autobiography".
    Autobiography
  - Josef Herman and the realist tradition among Jewish painters by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 36)
    Herman, Joseph
    Expressionism(Art)
  - Journal of a trip by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Published in Roditi's book, NEW HIEROGLYPHIC TALES, Kayak Press, San Francisco, 1968.
  - Juan Breyten by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Published in exhibition catalogs for Galeries Claude Levene, Paris, and Galerie Espana(?), Amsterdam.
    Breyten, Juan
    Art, Dutch
    Expressionism
  - Juifs dans l'art russe by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Art, Russian--History
  - Juifs dans l'art sovietique by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
  - Kafka's Beim Bau des Chinesischen Mauers by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Roditi's introduction for an edition of Kafka's Beim Bau der Chinesischen Mauer, published by Milos Sovak, 1975.
    Kafka, Franz. Beim Bau der Chinesischen Mauer.
  - Karaitism and sabbataeanism in Isaac Bashevis Singer's "The Slave" by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 36)
    Published in MIDSTREAM, New York, 1978.
    Singer, Isaac Bashevis
    Fiction--History and criticism
  - Kungliga Djurgaarden by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Poetry. Chicago.
  - Laganne a la Galerie Stadler by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    With the manuscript is an exhibition catalog for Laganne, Galerie Stadler, Paris, 9-29 March 1956.
    Laganne
    Artists, French
  - Larbaud le Bovaryste by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    With Roditi's note that this was published in VALERY LARBAUD: LA PROSE DU MONDE by Presses Universitaires de France, 1982, pages 119-135.
    Larbaud, Valery
    French literature--History and criticism
  - Larbaud le Bovaryste by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
  - Lectures a propos de la lecture by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Literature, Modern--15th and 16th centuries--History and criticism
    Sceve, Maurice
    Hebreu, Leon
  - Leon l'Hebreu et Maurice Sceve by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Sceve, Maurice--Biography
  - Leon Pierre-Quint's unfinished novel by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Pierre-Quint, Leon
    Authors, French--Biography
  - Letter from Germany by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Intellectuals
    Denazification
    Propaganda
  - Letter from Lisbon by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Published in NEW LEADER, New York, 12 November 1962.
    Portugal
    Politics
    Salazar
  - Letter from Lisbon by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    With Roditi's note that this was written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, but unpublished because it was lost in the mail.
    Art, Portugal
    Art and society
  - Letter from Marrakech by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Art, Moroccan--History
  - Letter from Tangier by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Tangier
    Archeological museums and collections
  - Life in a ryokan, or: An illiterate in Japan by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Japan--description and travel
    Travel--anecdotes, facetiae, satire, etc.
  - Lights on darkness by Roditi, Edouard., 1931?. (Box 36)
    Roditi notes on page 1 that this manuscript, unpublished, was written ca. 1931.
    Symbolism
  - Literary letter about East Berlin by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Published in NEW YORK TIMES BOOK REVIEW.
    Germany, Eastern
  - Literature of the Sefardim by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Published in BOOKS, London, Autumn 1974. With the manuscript is another copy (photocopy).
    Literature, Sephardic--History
  - Literature, the expression of an inner life by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Literature
    Culture
  - Little Danish rhapsody by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Roditi, Edouard. Promenade durch Tivoli.
    Published in MONAT, Berlin, no. 13 (1949) under the title "Promenade durch Tivoli."
    Copenhagen
  - Louis Latapie, a la Galerie Rive Gauche by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Latapie, Louis
    Dubuffet, Jean
  - Lunar nature of Krajcberg's art by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Krajcberg
    Art, Polish
  - Michel Kikoine by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Kikoine, Michel
    Art, Russian
    Art--Biography
  - Michel Kikoine by Roditi, Edouard., n.d.; [1 of 3 folders] (Box 36)
    English translation of Roditi's French monograph on Michel Kikoine.
  - Michel Kikoine by Roditi, Edouard., n.d.; [2 of 3 folders] (Box 36)
    French version.
  - Michel Kikoine by Roditi, Edouard., n.d.; [3 of 3 folders] (Box 36)
    With Roditi's note that this was written for an art book on Russian-Jewish painter Michel Kikoine, published in 1973 by Editions d'Art Piazza.
  - Raphael Levy by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Ryvel, pseud.
    Supplied title. Appended to this manuscript is a letter, ca. Christmas 1982, to "Dear Brad," noting enclosure of this bio-bibliography.
    Authors, Tunisian--Biography
  - Roger Loewig by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 36)
    Roditi's English text was translated into German for a Loewig exhibition catalogue, Baukunst Gallery, Cologne, 1973.
    Loewig, Roger
    Art, German
    Disasters--Psychological aspects
  - Manuscript found in old Vali by Anonymous. (Box 37)
    Fiction--Stories, plots, etc.
    Jews in Turkey--Anecdotes, facetiae, satire, etc.
  - Naufrage du Deutschland by Hopkins, Gerard Manley., [1 of 3 folders] (Box 37)
    French translation by ER. ER's note: Published in CAHIERS DU SUD, Marseilles.
  - Naufrage du Deutschland by Hopkins, Gerard Manley., [2 of 3 folders] (Box 37)
  - Naufrage du Deutschland by Hopkins, Gerard Manley., [3 of 3 folders] (Box 37)
  - 1982: Festival des peintres juifs de France by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Published IN L'ARCHE.
  - Lev Meshberg by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Published in J.A.C.O.B.'s Letter, San Francisco, Summer 1984.
    Meshberg, Lev
    Artists, Ukranian
  - Mal sacre by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Epileptics--Personal narratives
    Homosexuality
  - Man Ray, a l'Etoile Scellee by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    With the review is a Man Ray exhibition catalog, l'Etoile Scellee, Paris, April 1956.
    Ray, Man
    Artists
  - Manuel Cargaleiro: Prologomenes pour une esthetique de la ceramique by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Portuguese translation published in OCIDENTE, Lisbon, 1970.
    Cargaleiro, Manuel
    Art, Portuguese
  - Manuel Rendon, a la Galerie de Berri by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 37)
    With the review is a list of works exhibited at Galerie de Berri, Paris.
    Rendon, Manuel
    Art, Equadorian
  - Marcelle Cahn: le romantisme secret d'une oeuvre d'apparence classique by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Published in L'ARCHE, Paris, 1982.
    Cahn, Marcelle
  - Marcus Behmer, a master of art nouveau by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Behmer, Marcus
    Biography--History and criticism
  - Marwan by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Untitled manuscript. Text for Marwan exhibition catalogue, Gruenebaum Gallery, New York, 1978.
    Marwan
    Expressionism (Art)
  - Mary Guggenheim Ewalt by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Guggenheim, Mary Ewalt
    Women artists
  - Materialism and mysticism in Egyptian architecture by Roditi, Edouard., ca. 1931. (Box 37)
    Architecture, Egyptian
  - Mauvais sang by Roditi, Edouard., n.d.; [1 of 2 folders] (Box 37)
    With Roditi's note that this was the opening chapter for his French novel, Le Mauvais Sang, accepted for publication by Gallimard in 1937, but not published in 1940 because he was Jewish.
    Roditi, Edouard. Le Mauvais Sang.
  - Mauvais sang by Roditi, Edouard., ca. 1933-1934.; [2 of 2 folders] (Box 37)
    With Roditi's notes that these are parts of his novel, Le Mauvais Sang.
  - Meditation on books by Roditi, Edouard., 1966. (Box 37)
    With Roditi's note "For Kenneth Rexroth, in whose home this poem was written."
  - Mektub by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
  - Menschenreine Welt von Siegfried Klapper by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Klapper, Siegfried
    Magic realism (Art)
  - Merkado: Une sculpture qui "imite" des concepts by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Merkado
  - Metropolitan Museum de New York achete une toile russe by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Art industries and trade
  - Miguel Torga by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Das Lot. Berlin.
    With Roditi's note that this was written for DAS LOT, Berlin, but never published.
    Torga, Miguel
    Authors, Portuguese
  - Miloud Labied and contemporary Moroccan art by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 37)
    Written for BLAST, 1981, second issue.
    Labied, Miloud
    Art, Moroccan
  - Mise au point by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Published in HOMO 2000, Paris, no. 4, 1979.
    Change of sex
  - Mise au point by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Roditi, Edouard. Klaus Mann, le citoyen du monde.
    Published in HOMO 2000, Paris, no. 3, 1979. The second item is titled, "Klaus Mann, le citoyen du monde".
    Mann, Klaus
    Authors, German
  - Mois de consecrations tardives by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Published in L'ARCHE, Paris. This manuscript is written on the verso of pages from Roditi's manuscript for MAGELLAN OF THE PACIFIC.
  - Monde ambivalent des poupees anciennes by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 37)
    Puppets and puppet-plays
  - Monticelli, a la Gal[e]rie Caillieux by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Monticelli
  - Moroccan headaches by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Roditi, Edouard. North Africa's greatest migration.
    Published under the title "North Africa's greatest migration" in NEW LEADER, 20 September 1964.
    Alien labor, Moroccan
    Europe, Western
  - Morocco's monument and fine arts problems by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 37)
    Roditi, Edouard. Morocco's monuments and their conservation.
    Published under the title "Morocco's monuments and their conservation" in APOLLO, London.
    Morocco
    Museum conservation methods
  - Most magnificent oration, to be delivered by the author on the occasion of his accepting. by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Published in CONJUNCTIONS, no. 1, 1982.
    Auden, W.H.
    Speeches, addresses, etc.
    Nobel prizes
  - Mystery of the beginning by Roditi, Edouard., 1931, 1977. (Box 37)
    Title of the poem on the carbon copy is "Beginning and an end."
  - Mystery of the beginning by Roditi, Edouard., 1931, 1977. (Box 37)
  - Myths and marvels by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 37)
  - Naissance d'un classique by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Guimpel, Rene. Journal d'un collectionneur, marchand de tableaux.
  - Neo-cabbalism in the American-Jewish counter-culture by Roditi, Edouard., n.d.; [2 folders] (Box 37)
    American literature--Jewish authors
    Cabala
  - Neuhaus by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
  - New Guinea travelogue by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Travel
    New Guinea
  - New last will and testament by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 37)
    Published in EUROPEAN JUDAISM, London, 1967.
    Levy, Bernard-Henri. Le testament de Dieu.
    Authors, French--History and criticism
    Political science--Book reviews
  - News from the salt mines or the note-books of a superfluous citizen by Roditi, Edouard., n.d.; [2 folders] (Box 37)
    Signed by Edouard Roditi on page 1 with note "for Herbert Marcuse".
    Political satire
    Democracy
    Marcuse, Herbert
  - Non-existent French Jew by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Published under the title "The Jew in recent Franco-Jewish novels" in COMMENTARY, November 1956.
    Ikor, Roger. Les eaux melees.
    Literature--History and criticism
  - Notes on some of Yunus Emre's themes by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Emre, Yunus
    Turkish poetry--History and criticism
  - Novels of Italo Svevo by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 37)
    Svevo, Italo
    Italian literature
  - Nuits dans la cave by Tuerk, Werner., n.d. (Box 37)
    With ER's note that this is an "unpublished French translation of a story by German writer Werner Tuerk, published in [an] anthology of young German writers edited by Klaus Mann & Erich Ebermayer".
    Tuerk, Werner
    German fiction
  - Of cats and men by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Cats
  - On a rereading of the poems of Philip Freneau: A belated bicentennary celebration by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Written for Kenneth Rexroth. Published in PEARL, Odense, Denmark, 1979.
    Freneau, Philip
    American poetry--History and criticism
    Rexroth, Kenneth
  - On books that have remained abroad by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Written while Roditi was on the faculty at the University of Kansas.
    Library catalogs and readers
    Little magazines
  - Oriental tapestry exhibition by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Tapestry--Exhibitions
  - Origines et sources du terrorisme armenien by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Terrorism
    Armenian question
  - Other languages by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Jewish poetry in Europe
    Jewish poetry--History and criticism
  - Others by Roditi, Edouard., n.d.; [1-2 of 3 folders] (Box 38)
    Individualism
  - Others by Roditi, Edouard., n.d.; [3 of 3 folders] (Box 38)
    Written for Lawrence Fixel.
    Fixel, Lawrence
  - Oxford de Duns Scotus by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
  - Pacific: its peace and freedom by Roditi, Edouard., [1968].; [1 of 2 folders] (Box 38)
    Published under the title "Trouble in paradise" in NEW LEADER.
    Pacific settlement of international disputes
    Peaceful change (International relations)
  - Pacific: its peace and freedom by Roditi, Edouard., [2 of 2 folders] (Box 38)
    Monat. Berlin.
    Lacking pages 5, 6 and 10. Published under the title "Trouble in paradise" in NEW LEADER, 26 February 1968, and in a German translation in MONAT, Berlin.
  - Paintings of Shirley Goldfarb by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Roditi's note on page 1 indicates that this was published in an exhibition catalogue for a show at the Erik Locke Gallery, San Francisco.
    Goldfarb, Shirley
    Jawlensky
    Painting--Technique
  - Paris decouvre avec retard un inconnu deja celebre ailleurs by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    With Roditi's note on page 1 that this was published in L'ARCHE, Paris, 1982.
    Guggenheim, Willy
    Artists, Swiss
  - Paris galleries and museum review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York. This untitled article begins, "Galerie Passali, 33 rue de Miromesnil, is a new gallery that ..."
    Paris in art
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., 1972. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Published in L'ARCHE, Paris, November 1972. Article begins, "Depuis quelques mois, le Cabinet International d'Art Institic ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., 1975. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. With ER's note that this was published in L'ARCHE, Paris, 1975. Article begins "Tout cet hiver, le Jewish Museum de New York ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., 1976. (Box 38)
    With ER's note that this was published in L'ARCHE, Paris, 1976. This untitled article begins, "De meme que tous les ans, Janvier et Fevrier nous permettront de visiter de nouveau quelques galeries americaines ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., 1976. (Box 38)
    With ER's note that this was published in PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, 1976. Article begins, "From October 16 to October 24, most the leading Paris galleries ... "
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., 1976. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, 1976. Article begins, "Paris art-lovers have rarely been offered as rich and varied a bill of fare ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., 1977. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. With ER's note that this was published in PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, 1977. Article begins, "Two major exhibitions, in Paris galleries in January and February, highlighted what may well prove ... "
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., 1980. (Box 38)
    With Roditi's note on page 1, published in L'ARCHE, Paris, February 1980. This review begins "C'est avec beaucoup de tristesse ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Published in L'ARCHE, Paris. Article begins, "Nous venons d'apprendre le deces ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. With ER's note that this was published in PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, January 1978. Article begins, "Weary of the repetitiousness of most abstract art, Paris art-lovers have ... "
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Written for ARTS. Article begins, "Were there such as institution as a Mat-of- the-month Club ... "
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Published in L'ARCHE, Paris. Article begins, "Venu pour la premiere fois en France ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Article begins, "A la Galerie Blumenthal, Faubourg, Saint-Honore, une tres belle exposition ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York. Article begins, "When we at last get around to formulating a more historically objective and less hagiographic view of French Impressionism ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Written for L'ARCHE, Paris. Article begins, "Il me serait facile, chaque mois, de consacrer toute ma chronique de L'Arche ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York. Article begins, "Museums and privately-owned galleries ... have been busily reviving interest ... in Pre-raphaelite and Symbolist art."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 38)
    With ER's note that this was published in L'ARCHE, Paris, May-June 1976. Article begins, "La Galerie Hardy, 27 rue Guenegaud, est une de celles qui ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., [1 of 2 folders] (Box 38)
    Supplied title. Written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York. This untitled article begins, "May and June are traditionally the peak period of the Paris art-world's ..."
  - Paris galleries and museums review by Roditi, Edouard., [2 of 2 folders] (Box 38)
    Two copies. A article written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York. This untitled article begins, "May and June are traditionally the peak period of the Paris art-world's ..."
  - Paris gallery notes by Roditi, Edouard., 1974. (Box 38)
    Published in PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, 1974. This article begins, "It is often difficult for a critic to keep up with all of the Galerie Katia Granoff's many, varied and scattered activities ..."
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., 1957. (Box 38)
    With ER's note that this was published in ARTS Magazine, October 1957. This article begins, "The annual 'season' of the Paris art-world ..."
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., 1962. (Box 38)
    With ER's note that this was published in ARTS MAGAZINE, New York, July 1962. This article begins, "As one looks back on many of the more popular or surprising art-exhibitions of this year's summer-season in Paris ... "
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., 1975. (Box 38)
    With ER's note that this was published in PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, 1975. This article begins, "Though time may well be as hard on the Paris art-market as on Madison Avenue ... "
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., 1979. (Box 38)
    With ER's note that this was published in PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, March 1979. This article begins, "The monumental retrospective of the work of Rene Magritte ... "
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., 1980. (Box 38)
    With ER's note that this was published in PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, March 1980. This article begins, "A whole series of recent Paris one-man shows has stressed ..."
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Written for ARTS MAGAZINE, New York. This article begins, "A couple of years ago, I happened to call one day on an Amsterdam dealer ... "
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York. This article begins, "The objects represented in the twenty-one recent paintings and the one sculpture exhibited by Michel Tyszblat at the Galerie de Seine ... "
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    This is ER's last column for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York. This article begins, "As I now write this last Paris letter of a long series ... " With ER's corrected typescript is an uncorrected carbon copy.
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Published in ARTS Magazine, New York. This article begins, "The kaleidoscope of the Paris art-season ..." With the article are galley proofs with ER's holograph corrections and another copy of the article.
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 38)
    Written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York. This article begins, "One of the most successful and widely discussed one-man shows of the Fall season has been ... that of the Yugoslav neo- surrealist painter Dado ... "
  - Open letters to LE JOURNAL DE TANGER by Roditi, Edouard and Bowles, Paul., 1984]. (Box 38)
    Bowles, Paul
    Galley proofs for a contribution to BLAST 3, Santa Barbara. With this is a letter from Black Sparrow Press, 20 April 1984.
    Wit and humor
    American humorists
  - Poems by Pessoa, Fernando. (Box 39)
    ER's note: First drafts of his English translations of Pessoa, published in POETRY.
  - Poems by Pessoa, Fernando. (Box 39)
    Celan, Paul, trans.
    German translations from the Portuguese of Pessoa by Paul Celan and ER. This manuscript has corrections in Celan's hand. ER's note: Published in DIE NEUE RUNDSCHAU and Celan's collected works.
  - Fernando Pessoa: The poet as simulator by Roditi, Edouard. (Box 39)
    First published in the LITERARY REVIEW.
    Pessoa, Fernando
    Poets, Portuguese--Biography
  - Larbaud le Bovaryste by Roditi, Edouard., 1982. (Box 39)
    With Roditi's note that this was published in 1982 by Presses Universitaires de France in a volume devoted to a Larbaud symposium, 1981, University of Amiens.
    Authors, French
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., 1976. (Box 39)
    Written for PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, 1976. This article begins, "Except for shows in museums and other public institutions ... "
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., 1977. (Box 39)
    Published in PICTURES ON EXHIBIT, New York, October 1977. This article begins, "A great deal has already been written in Israel, Western Europe and the United States, about Jewish writers ... "
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 39)
    Written for ARTS MAGAZINE, New York. This article begins, "Living in Paris in this year of disgrace ... "
  - Paris letter by Roditi, Edouard., n.d. (Box 39)